A Guide to the Papers of the Noel Family,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Correspondence of the Noel Family
  - Kwangju, Korea; Yokohama, Japan, 1964, 59 items. (Box-folder 2:8)
    There are letters from Edgar and Jeanne to their parents about students demonstrating against the corruption in Korea. Edgar complains about the backward tendencies of the Koreans including their beliefs in the use of herbal medicines and acupuncture. He expresses relief at leaving Korea and mentions their next location of Yokohama, Japan.
    There is also news that they are having another child, Norbourn "Bruz." There is correspondence between Edgar and his parents about the genealogy of the Noel Family including a letter from Edmund (Ned) Berkeley, a former UVA classmate who worked at the Virginia State Archives. Edgar is researching his ancestor, [Norbon Noel] a Confederate doctor in the Civil War. There is also a personal letter from Congressman Thomas N. Downing to Edgar's parents in support of legislation to allow prayer in schools.
    Other correspondence includes a letter from Minnie Agnes George (Edgar's grandmother) to Edgar's parents, a letter from Bess Dietrich, and a printed brochure on the Kwangju Christian Hospital and Graham Tuberculosis Center.
  - Yokohama, Japan, 1965, 48 items. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Letters from Edgar to his parents about learning Japanese; about his next assignment in Fukuoka, Japan; about the publishing status of Edgar's poem and children's book; letters from Edgar's father which include a disparaging joke about Lyndon Johnson; a photograph of Wen and Laura with Santa Claus.
  - Fukuoka, Japan, 1966-1967, 86 items. (Box-folder 3:2)
    Letters from Edgar to his parents about his work and the many activities that he must attend including the Japan-America Cultural Conference; his efforts to encourage support for the Vietnam War; his meeting with the Governor and Vice-Governor of Nagasaki and invitations for the Peace Corps to Nagasaki.
    Other correspondence includes a letter from Jeanne's father, LeRoy S. Thompson [Roy] to Harriet Crawford Jones concerning genealogy information; and letters from Suetaka Hatanaka, the President of Minaminihon Broadcasting Co., thanking Edgar's parents for hosting him while he was in the United States. There are news clippings of Edgar in his role as the director of the Fukuoka American Cultural Center and brochures of the Shiroyama Kanko Hotel and Nagasaki.
  - Fukuoka, Japan; Bethesda, Maryland; Georgetown, Guyana, 1968-1971, 66 items. (Box-folder 3:3)
    Letters from Edgar about his new title as Consul and Secretary of the Embassy; the response of the Japanese press to atomic powered submarines; the death of Martin Luther King and Robert F. Kennedy, as well as the reaction of shock from the Japanese concerning such violence; an anti-Vietnam lecture by Edgar Snow; Edgar's attendance at a ceremony at the White House for the Japanese Prime Minister Sato; and a letter where Edgar describes "Negroes" and "East Indians."
    There are also letters from Edgar's parents telling him that Bill Ed Adkins, husband of his sister, Melissa, was dying; a letter from Edgar's sister; letters from Jeanne and Edgar's parents about genealogy; news that Edgar's book of poetry was to be published by the Fukuoka Japan-America Society; a letter from Lee Adkins to his grandparents Noel; letters from Ronnie and Bess Dietrich at the Kwangju Christian Hospital; and a letter from Aunt Mary (Mary Virginia Noel Evans) to Edgar's parents. There is an excerpt of Edgar's article, Stephen Crane: A Realist who Painted with Words 1970.
  - Georgetown, Guyana, 1972, 73 items. (Box-folder 3:4)
    Letters from Edgar to his parents about Georgetown, Guyana; his feelings of disappointment with the foreign service; his attempts to counter anti-Vietnam War propaganda; comparisons of Surinam and Guyana and their relationship with the Dutch; and negative comments about "Bush Negroes" as Africans.
    Other family letters mention the Nixon and McGovern Presidential election, as well as Ronald Reagan, and Barry Goldwater; Jeanne writes about "Hippies-Zippies" impeding the delegates access to the convention, and terrorism at the Olympic Games. Edgar's parents complain about "blacks" moving into the neighborhood and express excitement about men landing on the moon. The children write to their grandparents. There is a letter from the Dietrich's, and a news clipping about the death of Edgar's aunt, Mary VirginiaNoel Evans. There are photographs of Edgar's new home in Georgetown.
  - Georgetown, Guyana, 1973, 117 items. (Box-folder 3:5)
    Letters from Edgar and Jeanne, and their parents supporting Nixon during Watergate. Edgar also writes about how the press ignores the progress that America has made in civil rights. In other letters, he mentions budget cuts; Senator J. William Fulbright; Democracy; Fidel Castro, and Cuba's close relationship with the Soviet Union. His letters also mention Prime Minister Burnham, the elections in Guyana, and how the parties are divided between the Blacks and the East Indians. Edgar also mentions Cheddi Jagan, a famous communist leader, who blames America for the setbacks of the local government, but then turns to America when Guyana needs money. Edgar writes that President Nixon is less tolerant of this behavior than President Kennedy.
    Jeanne writes a letter of praise about her former professor, Jon Kirby, to Randolph Macon Woman's College. There are also report cards for the children.
  - Georgetown, Guyana, 1974 January-July, 65 items. (Box-folder 3:6)
    Letters from Edgar about his next assignment and promotion as Deputy Public Affairs Officer in Lagos, Nigeria; his resentment at having so little personal time with his family; his description of a corrupt Guyana government that runs out of money, taxes its people, and allows muggings to occur without any policing; and letters from Jeanne and Edgar's parents about their visit to Fort Myers; Edgar's mother, Lelia Noel, has a stay in the hospital with a broken hip. There is also a letter from Edgar's sister, Melissa, about her happiness and her marriage to Don Norman; and a letter from Melissa's son, Lee Adkins to Edgar.
  - Georgetown, Guyana, 1974 August-December, 53 items. (Box-folder 3:7)
    Letters from Edgar about finishing his annual efficiency reports on his staff; and preparing for an Alister Cooke TV series, "America." He also writes about Nixon's resignation and his hopes for the upcoming Ford presidency. He mentions his concerns about the kidnapping of a United States Information Agency officer and close friend, Barbara Hutcheson, in Santo Domingo. There is a news clipping from the local paper that attacks Edgar and the U. S. Government for supporting the Reynolds Aluminum Mines. Edgar accuses the Guyanese government of being like children who want to play when there is work to be done. He writes about the laziness of the "negro" and hopes the United States Government will "dump the whole lot."
    Other correspondence includes a letter from Lee Adkins, son of Melissa Noel Adkins, to his grandparents Noel; postcards from Edgar, Jeanne, and the children during their trip to England; and letters from Edgar and Jeanne's parents.
  - Lagos, Nigeria, 1975, 57 items. (Box-folder 4:1)
    Letters from Edgar to his parents about the need for Washington to recognize Nigeria as a major oil producer and as the most important country in Africa; descriptions of the various people living in Nigeria from well educated, and oil "rednecks" to the local people. He also writes about Harmatan dust storms, seeing a camel caravan, and his meeting with "the Oba (King) of Benin." He also mentions Mrs. Coretta King's visit and writes that he would rather honor Robert E. Lee over Martin Luther King any day. He also says, "I hope to never serve in Africa again-it will be difficult just to go in to Newport News. I'm not impressed with the blacks."
    Letters from his parents indicate that his sister, Melissa Adkins, is rescued from Weston Mental Hospital, and is separated from her new husband. There has been little news from her son, Lee. There is also a letter from Edgar's friend, Bert E. McCormick, who is now a minister at The First Church in Albany.
  - Lagos, Nigeria, 1976, 127 items. (Box-folder 4:2)
    Letters from Edgar to his parents about an attempted coup by Lieutenant Colonel Buka Suka Dimka against General Murtala Muhammed. The attempted coup was in response to Muhammed's anti-corruption campaigns and opposition to United States policy in Angola. Edgar's letters describe the aftermath of the coup, the imposed curfew, and false accusations that blame the attempted coup on "the dark hand of the CIA." He writes that Nigeria "has become rampant xenophobic," but assures his parents that his family is safe. Edgar repeats his comment that the underdeveloped countries always blame America. He suggests, "that we close our Embassies in half of them, especially in Africa and go home." He also mentions the 1976 presidential debates and his disappointment with Jimmy Carter.
    There is also an article titled Goldwater Blows the Whistle on His Mates; U. S. News & World Report February 16, 1976 and other news clippings, discussing the attempted coup and the subsequent execution of the Commissioner for Defence, Major General Illiya. There is also a copy of Nigeria's largest daily publication, The Daily Times for Friday, March 12, 1976.
    There is also information on boarding schools, Fork Union Military Academy and Staunton Hall School for Girls, as there is no school beyond 10th grade in Nigeria. Edgar's sister, Melissa, has a good job and has moved into her own apartment. Her son, Lee Adkins, is getting married; There is also a letter from Bess Dietrick.
  - Lagos, Nigeria, 1977 January-August, 98 items. (Box-folder 4:3)
    Edgar writes about the Second World Black Arts Festival that was being hosted by the Nigerians. He is concerned that it will be poorly run because of the lack of services (water, electricity, sewage) in Nigeria. The food was being flown in by Swiss Air at a cost of two million dollars per day for six weeks. He writes, "How about that for waste, inefficiency, and having more oil money than brains." He also writes that "American Blacks" will not like the conditions very much, especially the local robberies. He even mentions that dead bodies of people who have been murdered are found in the water near his backyard. He writes that he is frustrated with the "bad conditions, corruption, stupidity and disregard for human rights and democracy" in Lagos and other underdeveloped countries. He also writes about his disdain for President Jimmy Carter. On a positive note, he highly praises the work of Alex Haley in Roots.
    Other correspondence between family members reveals that Laura Noel starts school at Staunton Hall for Girls, in Virginia and Wen Noel starts school at Fork Union Military Academy also in Virginia. Jeanne's parents relocated to Fort Myers, Florida.
  - Lagos, Nigeria, 1977 September-December, 109 items. (Box-folder 4:4)
    Edgar writes about the International Trade Fair in Lagos which was a huge success. He received high praise for the USIS part of the exhibit. There is also excitement about President Jimmy Carter and First Lady, Rosalind Carter, visiting Lagos. However their visit was postponed. Edgar writes more about the savage behavior of the people and that the society was better when it was under British rule.
    There is also correspondence with Wen and Laura while they attended Fork Union and Staunton Hall for Girls. Wen was made First Class Sargent with five stripes after only a few months and Laura was the star in a play production at school. Correspondence also reveals that Edgar's mother, Lelia Noel, was suffering a great deal with asthma.
  - Lagos, Nigeria, 1978 January-April, 71 items. (Box-folder 4:5)
    Edgar writes about his promotion to Foreign Service Information Officer Two which is a top ranking in the agency. He mentions the visit of President Carter and his family to Lagos, and the performance of jazz pianist, Memphis Slim in Nigeria. Edgar writes that the Nigerians do not like jazz as they "are barely above the tom-tom level in music appreciation." Concerning the visit of President Carter, Edgar writes, "I wish Carter would stay home and solve the coal strike, handle the Panama issue, get an energy bill passed, and in general look after our own country rather than mess around here in Africa. The Democratic Party really needs the Black vote I guess since they may lose the Jewish vote."
  - Lagos, Nigeria, 1978 May-September, 82 items. (Box-folder 4:6)
    Edgar writes about showing the mini-series Roots in Nigeria and the attitudes of Nigerians towards African Americans. Edgar and his father write about their support for Proposition 13, a bill in California to cut property taxes.
    Other correspondence is from the Noel children, Norbourn (Bruz) writes from Woodberry Forest School, William (Wen) writes from Fork Union Military Academy, and Laura writes from Staunton Hall for Girls to their parents and grandparents.
  - Lagos, Nigeria, 1978 October-December, 131 items. (Box-folder 5:1)
    Edgar writes about a possible new position in Bombay, India. He also mentions a hepatitis and meningitus scare, as well as the horrible news of a mass suicide in Guyana with Jim Jones. Edgar also writes about an intelligence agent who was pretending to be a student, and was asking questions about American Intelligence.
    Other correspondence mentions that Wen makes the National Honor Society. There are also programs for Woodberry Forest School Parents Weekend and a Fork Union Military Academy football program.
  - Lagos, Nigeria, 1979 January, 54 items. (Box-folder 5:2)
    Jeanne Noel writes that the Nigerians are obnoxious and Jeanne's mother writes about her concern over the demonstrations of the Iranian students. Jeannette also mentions her frustration with the democrats. Edgar's father writes that President Carter is abusing Virginia because the state did not vote for him. He writes, "The place for him is back in Georgia gnawing peanuts."
  - Lagos, Nigeria, 1979 February, 109 items. (Box-folder 5:3)
    Edgar mentions visitors, David Rockefeller, president of Chase Manhattan Bank, who flew in on his private jet; and Maynard Jackson, Mayor of Atlanta. Edgar is writing an article on Townsend Harris, the first American diplomat in Japan. There is also a news clipping about the attack of the United States Embassy in Tehran by a group of leftist Guerillas.
  - Lagos, Nigeria, 1979 March-April (Box-folder 5:4)
    Edgar praises Mayor Maynard Jackson of Atlanta for his great speaking voice and sense of humor. In other news from home, Edgar's uncle, Jim Wash, dies. Wen was promoted to First Lieutenant. There are also photographs of the family at spring break in Fort Myers, Florida.
  - Bombay, India, 1979 May-October, 110 items. (Box-folder 5:5)
    Edgar accepts a new position in Bombay, India. He describes the Indians as being efficient and friendly, although he says that Indian bureaucracy "beats any other country's." Jeanne's mother writes that there are odd and even days for obtaining gas in the United States. There is also a news clipping about Edgar titled, Noel, USICA Director, in The Free Press Journal.
    Edgar's friend, Dob. writes about helping Wen get accepted into Westpoint. There are also letters from Harry F. Byrd, Jr. and John W. Warner in reference to Wen's application to Wespoint.
  - Bombay, India, 1979 November-December, 80 items. (Box-folder 5:6)
    Edgar writes about violent demonstrations by Iranian students; and Americans that were burned and murdered in Islamabad. Edgar's Christmas letter gives a description of the politics in India. President Carter stopped oil shipments from Iran to the United States. Edgar writes that the Noels feel safe because of the excellent police security in Bombay. Jeanne writes a description of New Delhi and Old Delhi to Norbourn (Bruz).
    There are more letters regarding referrals for Wen from John Warner, Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Paul Trible, Ralph E. Martin, staff assistant for Vice President, Walter Mondale, and from K. T. Whitescarver, president of Fork Union Military Academy. Laura is accepted into Randolph Macon Woman's College. There is a photograph of Wen at Fork Union.
  - Bombay, India, 1980 January-March, 109 items. (Box-folder 5:7)
    Edgar writes about his concern that Indira Gandhi is supportive of Russia and has been elected Prime Minister Gandhi. He compares Russia's attack [on Afghanistan] to Hitler's invasion of Czechoslovakia in 1939. He also mentions that the Indians are worried about the United States sending arms to Pakistan. He writes that he is surprised that the Indians are afraid of a natural event, such as a solar eclipse, but are sophisticated enough to make an atom bomb.
    Edgar mentions Muhammad Ali who came for a boxing exhibition and departs for Africa to discuss the Olympic boycott. He writes that "Ali must never read the papers to be so dumb about the African South Africa situation." Edgar also describes a dinner with former Attorney General, Archibald Cox, and describes him as " a delightful man and easy to talk to."
    Letters from Jeanne's parents indicate that they believe that Wen is accepted into Westpoint and the Noels are ecstatic. (It turns out that only an interview has been granted.)
  - Bombay, India, 1980 April-September, 112 items. (Box-folder 6:1)
    Edgar writes that he becomes angry when the Indians say that the Russians were invited to Afghanistan and people blame the United States for arming the rebels. Many American Offices were closed due to the heightened tensions from Iranian students. There was a failed attempt to rescue the American hostages in Iran. Edgar is concerned that there might be a third world war. The American Center in Delhi was besieged with Iranian students and they burned an effigy of President Carter. He also writes that he feels that the United States Intelligence Agency is treating the agents in the field unfairly.
    Edgar's father, William Noel, died of a heart attack. Enclosed with other letters is a newsletter and calendar from Virginia Military Institute.
  - Bombay, India, 1980 October-December, 89 items. (Box-folder 6:2)
    Edgar writes that India abstained in the United Nations vote requesting Russian troops to leave Afghanistan. He is very disappointed in the Indians lack of belief in "justice, morality and non-alignment." He also writes that Prince Charles of Wales is in Bombay for a visit.
    Included in the correspondence is a theatre program of a play at Randolph Macon Woman's College.
  - Bombay, India, 1981 January-May, 103 items. (Box-folder 6:3)
    Correspondence refers to confirmation hearings on General Alexander Haig, as the Secretary of State. The Noel's give high praise for Haig and criticize Lyndon Johnson. The letters also mention President Reagan's budget cuts and the attempted assassination on Reagan's life.
    Jeanne writes to her parents about the death of Edgar's mother, Lelia Noel. Norbourn (Bruz) writes that Joe Theisman visits his school, Woodberry Forest.
  - Bombay, India, 1981 June-December, 63 items. (Box-folder 6:4)
    There is mention of the assassination of Anwar Sadat. Other correspondence includes a letter of commendation for Wen from Virginia Military Institute and a VMI Calendar of Events.
  - Bombay, India, 1982 January-July, 103 items. (Box-folder 6:5)
    There was a mob attack on the American Consulate in Bombay. Laura writes to her parents about her speaking out against Jerry Falwell in a debate between Sam Brown and Moral Majority spokesperson, Cal Thomas at her school.
  - Bombay, India 1982 August-December, 90 items. (Box-folder 6:6)
    Jeanne writes to Laura about the birth of Lee and Carol Adkins' new baby, Lesley (Melissa's granddaughter).
  - Virginia Military Institute Grade Report, 1981-1982, 5 items. (Box-folder 6:7)
    Report card.
  - Bombay, India, 1983 January-May, 130 items. (Box-folder 6:8)
    Jeanne writes to Laura about Edgar's retirement. Wen writes to his parents about [the bombing] in Beirut. Edgar writes to Bruz that author and historian Daniel Boorstein is visiting in Bombay.
  - Bombay, India, 1983 June-December, 77 items. (Box-folder 7:1)
    There are letters about the United States invasion of Grenada. William (Wen) writes about his girlfriend, Ann. Laura writes that she is student teaching.
  - Bombay, India, 1984 January-June, 102 items. (Box-folder 7:2)
    Jeanne's mother, Jeanette, writes about the death of Yuri Andropov. Edgar writes that he is frustrated with his job and will retire from the State Department in September. Edgar also writes that India is in the news with the insurrection in Punjab.
  - Bombay, India, 1984 July-December, 65 items. (Box-folder 7:3)
    Jeanne's mother mentions the assassination of Indira Gandhi and the candidacy of Walter Mondale and Geraldine Ferrro. Norbourn "Bruz" writes that he is going to the World's Fair in New Orleans. William "Wen" writes that he is in Army Artillery School and has been named Artillery Officer.
  - Denbigh, Virginia, 1985, 45 items. (Box-folder 7:4)
    Photograph of Wen's girlfriend, Beth [Wisotckey]. Wen is stationed in Germany. Bruz is studying architecture in Italy. Laura receives a marriage proposal from her boyfriend from India. Leroy Thompson mentions tobacco stocks and how they will be affected by lawsuits against tobacco companies.
  - Denbigh, Virginia, 1986, 90 items. (Box-folder 7:5)
    Edgar writes to local delegate, Herbert H. Batemen, in support of freedom fighters in Nicaragua. Wen is stationed in Camp LeJeune and is engaged to Beth. Laura has a new boyfriend and Bruz is interning as an architect in Melbourne Australia.
  - Denbigh, Virginia, 1987-1988, 80 items. (Box-folder 7:6)
    Edgar buys a boat and names it the Ida J. He writes occasional letters to the editor of The Daily Press. In other correspondence, there is a copy of a letter written by famous scientist Arthur C. Clarke. Jeanne writes about her genealogy. Wen is performing artillery practice exercises in France, Morroco, Spain, and Lisbon. He breaks up with Beth due to conflicts in their careers and marries Kim Waters Noel. She becomes pregnant with their first child. His next station is in New York City. There is a photograph of Wen in his airplane. There are church programs from the Abingdon Episcopal Church (where Edgar is mentioned as a candidate for praying and laying of the hands) and Saint Raphael's Church.
  - Denbigh, Virginia, 1989-1992, 90 items. (Box-folder 7:7)
    There are various political letters and correspondence including letters between Edgar and the Right Reverend Peter James Lee, Diocese of Virginia, about Nelson Mandela; a letter from Chuck Robb regarding crimes committed by Oliver North; and a letter from Herbert H. Batemen, House of Representatives, about Edgar's support for H. R.1227 (a bill that supports prohibition of imposing taxes on out of state residents). Bert McCormick writes to Edgar about events in China... There is a news clipping about the celebration of the USS Newport News; a brochure about Paris; and a juror handbook.
    Wen and Kim have two daughters, Caroline and Tara. Bruz is working architectural jobs in Fort Lauderdale, Florida and is engaged to Kimberly Lynne Woods.
  - Genealogy, 1994, 3 items. (Box-folder 7:8)
    There is a form filled out with the lineage of Edgar Estes Noel II from 1599 to 1988. There is also a history of William Edgar Noel (1897-1981) and Edgar Estes Noel II (1933-present [1994]) which includes Wen, Laura, and Bruz, as well as their spouses and children.
    OS Daily Times newspaper March 12, 1976 and greeting card [1974] from Laura Noel to her father.